Whenever we go to buy a health insurance policy,
we definitely check two ratios.
These are the Incurrence Claim Ratio (
ICR) and the Claim Settlement Ratio (
CSR). Through these, we check the
working style of the health insurance company, how
it performs in terms of paying claims, what has been
its past track
record. But did you
notice one thing? If you have been following Insurance Impact's
videos for a long time, then
you must have noticed that we do not include CSR and Incurrence Claim Ratio in our health
insurance plan comparison videos
or even in the videos of normal health insurance plans.
What is the reason behind this? Are these figures wrong
or do I not trust these figures
or is the decision we take with these ICR and Claim Settlement Ratio to
choose the best health insurance policy
wrong? We will discuss this topic in detail
in today's video and all the
opinions and thoughts that we have.  The opinions expressed in this video are
my own, but I'm
using this video as an open debate.
If you agree or disagree with my views,
or have any other opinions, please share them
in the comments section. Let's
not delay and quickly begin the video. To
understand this topic in detail,
first, we need to understand the definitions of these two ratios: the Income
Claim Ratio and the Claim Settlement Ratio. Let's
first understand the Income Claim Ratio.
How much money do insurance companies
collect as premiums from policyholders throughout the year, and
how much of that money is returned to policyholders as claims.
This is
measured by the Claim Settlement Ratio. If
an insurance company has a
low Income Claim Ratio, it means that the company is being stingy in distributing claims.
It collected more money
but disbursed a lower amount of claims. On the
other hand, if a health insurance
company has a high Income Claim Ratio (ICR), then
it is quite lean.  This means that they may
feel a shortage of claim funds without any reason, and
they may face difficulty in paying even the necessary claims.
Now, suppose an insurance
company collected ₹1 as a health
insurance premium and
distributed 70 claims out of it, then the
income claim ratio (ICR) of this health insurance company is
70. Now, friends, let's
understand the claim settlement ratio (
CSR). The number of
claims a company settles out of every 100 claims is called the
claim settlement ratio of this health insurance company. If
an insurance company settles
90 claims out of 100 claims in a year, then the
CSR (Claim Settlement
Ratio) of this health insurance company is 90. But now both these ratios
appear to be very important from their definitions. Now, I am
not saying that you should not use
these figures or these ratios when choosing your health insurance policy,
but
why do I not rely on them too much or
refer to them too much? There are
two reasons behind this.  The first reason is
that these ratios, ICR and
CSR, have no direct connection with the
claim rejection or approval of your health insurance policy.
Many
policy holders, looking at these figures,
form the picture that this health
insurance company has a
very good claim settlement ratio and an excellent income
ratio. So, if I receive a
claim in the future, the
company will approve it too because this company has been
doing this. However, individual claim
approval or rejection depends on the
treatment I am taking under my health insurance policy. Has the
waiting period for this treatment ended? Is
this treatment
covered under my health insurance policy? Am
I taking this treatment in a blacklisted
hospital? That is, whether
my claim is approved or rejected will depend largely on my individual decisions and the coverage of the policy. There is no direct connection between this
claim ratio and the claim settlement ratio.
Now
comes the second point: this claim.  Ratio
means if an insurance company has a
very good income claim ratio, meaning it is
paying a lot of claims, does it make
any difference to your direct policy? A
health insurance company is a claim
that must be approved. It cannot deny something that is covered in your policy. Even
if it
denies it, we
can challenge that claim and we will get our claim
because that coverage is given in the policy
and this treatment is covered in that policy. The
insurance company is guaranteed not to
give you any claim that is not covered. Income ratio means
how much money the insurance company
collected as premium and how much
money it distributed among the policyholders as claims.
But suppose in a quarter
or a year, an insurance company
launched a very good plan and it became
very popular. For example, recently
III Lord launched the Elevate plan.
A few months ago, Rish 2.0 was
quite popular. Some time ago, when the NV Aspire
plan was launched, it also became very popular.
So, suppose when these plans become popular,
insurance companies collect a good amount of
premium from the market and it is
possible that the
claim company's incurrence ratio may decrease in this proportion,
but this does not have any negative impact
directly on your health insurance policy
because this incurrence ratio has decreased
due to increase in sales and not due to
denial of claims or due to fewer claims.
Now the second reason for
not using or referring these ratios is even more
solid than the first reason. That reason is that this
data of anchored claim ratio and
claim settlement ratio is absolute, that is, it is
very old data. Brother, first of all let's
talk about incurrence ratio. The
latest data of incurrence ratio is the
annual report of IRDA of 2022.
In it, incurrence claim ratios of all the health
insurance companies have been given,
but which year is currently going on? It is still going on.
2024-25 This is a 2-year-old
story. How can I refer to 2-year-old data
to decide how an
insurance company is doing? Now, suppose there is a
cricketer named Rohit Sharma. Let's
take an exam. How Rohit Sharma
performed in a series 2 years ago,
how many runs he scored, what difference does it make?
This has no relation to
how he will perform in today's match.
If we want to see his performance in today's match,
we will have to look at his form in this series.
We can depend on him or
predict how he will perform only on the basis of how he has performed in the last one or two months of this season. So,
I don't think these 2-year-old card claim ratios are of any use.
Now, after the card claim ratio, comes the
claim settlement ratio data, that is, the
latest claim settlement ratio data
available with us. The
IRDA annual report that I am
talking about is the report of 2022.  There is no figure by the
name of claim settlement ratio in the report that has come.
In this report,
which health insurance company has
made how many claims, this number of
claims is mentioned. If a person goes and reads this report and
wants to understand, he will not be able to understand and will get
completely confused as to what is the
claim settlement ratio of which health insurance company.
Whereas if IRD wanted, with
due respect, it could have
given the data of claim settlement ratio in this report,
but this is also a report of 2022, what is the use of
claim settlement ratio of a 2 year old report.
Now you will say that
health insurance companies
declare their claim settlement ratio every year themselves.
Now brother, that is self-declared data.
Now I will say this like this that there is
a saying in our Haryana that
who will tell that my seet is sour. Seet means
lassi, that is, tea. Who will tell that my lassi is
sour? Who in my own company will
say that my claim settlement ratio is low?
I am not suggesting here
that the insurance  Companies manipulate data and
tamper with it, but
this can happen. We need credible data
that has been issued by the regulatory authority, i.e., IRDA,
and is also the latest. There is an
advantage in using that data. For example,
suppose our children go
to school. They have monthly unit
tests and quarterly
exams as well. Only then can we check
whether the children are on track or not,
how are the children performing,
how is the school staff performing,
how is the school reporting, only then will we be
able to check because things have to be evaluated timely.
Now, these
health insurance companies also tell the investors, i.e., those whose money is invested,
how many policies have they
sold in this quarter, how many claims have they settled, then
why not tell this to the policy holders?
Policy holders also pay their hard-earned
premium to the insurance companies,
so it is their right that this data
reaches them. Here, the same thing is happening that
after using MDH spices for 100 years, now we  It is being found that it
contains carcinogenic
substances. When Horlicks and Monvi
came to India, the
initial children who used to drink them are now 40-45 years old.
Then we are noticing that it contains
50% sugar, that is why we have to
check the facts, challenge them
and
also challenge the unfounded notions that have been going on so that the
truth can come out
and the reality can come to the surface. Now
I have talked about these big brands
which are 100, 200, 200 years old brands,
if we
cannot check their credibility without questioning, challenging, or testing, then how can you check this only with these
two ratios - claim settlement ratio and
income claim ratio, the data of which is also old,
how
can you believe that your company
is good or not? Now the
only purpose of the conclusion of the video was to tell that I am not trusting my
videos.  Why don't I use these ratios?
I would request the
respected IRDA and
insurance companies to release the latest data.
Through this video, I'm
not trying to suggest that these figures are wrong.
My only intention is that
IRDA and insurance companies should release such data and
ratios that are up-to-
date and latest, so that
policyholders can use these data with complete reliability when
purchasing their policies. Now, I also
request policyholders: when you
buy a health insurance policy and
see these ratios, you should definitely
use them. I have no problem with that.
But first, check the major features:
your policy's coverage, cashless
hospitals, your sum insured, and the
rest of the policy's features.
Then, you should use these ratios.
This is their ideal weighting. I
hope this video has
created some clarity for you.
If you also feel this way, if you
agree with these ideas, you can like the video and share it
wherever necessary.
If you agree with these things, please like the video and share it wherever necessary.  If you disagree,
you can also tell us by commenting in the comment section of this video. We will
continue this discussion in the comment section as well. If you have been
associated with the Insurance Impact channel and videos for a long time and
you have not yet subscribed to the channel, then
please do subscribe to the channel.
I, Harvinder Singh, now take your permission. I will take your
permission in the next video. Till then,
take care of yourself, stay happy and
stay healthy. Jai Hind.